

Subhadeep Sarkar

Assistant Professor, Brandeis University Department of Computer Science

Contact No.: +1 (617) 372-3085

 $E\hbox{-}mail: subhadeep@brandeis.edu; subhadeepsarkarybs@gmail.com\\$

Website: subhadeep.net

Google Scholar: tinyurl.com/sarkar-gs

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in designing **privacy-aware data systems**. I work at the intersection of designing **data layouts and access methods for storage engines** and developing **systems-level solutions for privacy protection** in modern data systems. The goal of my research is to bridge the gap between the legal requirements and database systems designs by navigating the privacy-performance tradeoff and designing privacy-aware data structures and algorithms.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

07/2023 - present	Assistant Professor at Brandeis University, MA, USA Department of Computer Science
01/2019 - 06/2023	Post-doctoral Associate at Boston University, MA, USA Department of Computer Science, College of Arts & Sciences Advisor: Manos Athanassoulis.
01/2023 - 05/2023 01/2020 - 05/2020	Lecturer at Boston University, MA, USA Department of Computer Science, College of Arts & Sciences
02/2017 - 10/2018	Post-doctoral Researcher at Inria Rennes – Bretagne Atlantique, France <i>Advisor</i> : Christine Morin
07/2013 - 06/2017	Ph.D. Scholar at Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India Department of Computer Science & Engineering; School of Medical Science & Technology <i>Advisors</i> : Sudip Misra and Chandan Chakraborty.
10/2014 - 09/2016	Senior Research Fellow at Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India Department of Computer Science & Engineering
04/2013 - 09/2014	Junior Research Fellow at Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India School of Information Technology

EDUCATION

2013 - 2017	Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India Specialization: Wireless communication in sensor networks Dissertation: "Analysis of Delay in Wireless Communication for Healthcare Systems"
2008 - 2012	Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.) Institute of Engineering and Management, Kolkata, India Specialization: Computer Science and Engineering Dissertation: "One World Vigilant Online Surveillance System"

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- 2022 Invited for a full talk at the **invitation-only workshop** on *High Performance Transaction Systems (HPTS)*.
- 2020 | Selected for a **spotlight talk** at *North-East Database Day (NEDBD)*.
- 2018 | Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions Seal of Excellence by the European Commission. [*url*]
- 2016 | Selected as **Most qualified young scientist** to attend the 4th Heidelberg Laureate Forum, Germany.
- 2015 Second best Ph.D. Thesis award at the 5th IDRBT Doctoral Colloquium organized by Institute for Development and Research in Banking Technology (IDRBT).
- Senior research fellowship from the Ministry of Human Resource Development (MHRD), Govt. of India (*fellowship duration*: 10/2015 09/2016).
- 2015 | International travel grant from Ministry of Human Resource Development, Govt. of India for IEEE ICC.
- Honorary certificate of appreciation from the IEEE Communications Society at the IEEE ComSoc Student Competition.
- Research fellowship from the Department of Electronics and Information Technology, Govt. of India (fellowship duration: 04/2013 09/2015).
- 2012 | Ranked 1885 (among 156,782 candidates) nationally in Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE).
- 2010 | **Ranked** among the **top 2**% in 6th National Aptitude Test held by NIIT.
- National Merit scholarship of Government of India for securing a state rank of 37 (among 764,933 candidates) in secondary board examination.

PUBLICATIONS

Patents

INDIAN PATENT 2016 **S. Sarkar**, S. Chatterjee, S. Misra, E. A. Ansari, D. Ghatak, S. Sarkar, "A Privacy-Aware Ambulatory Healthcare System Using Wireless Body Area Networks (WBANs)", Indian Patent, File no.: 201631000214, 2016.

Books

CRC PRESS T&F 2019 S. Misra, **S. Sarkar**, and S. Chatterjee, "Sensors, Cloud, and Fog: The Enabling Technologies for the Internet of Things", *CRC Press, Taylor & Francis Group*, ISBN 9780367196127, 2019.

Journals and Journal-Equivalent Conference Papers

ToDS 2023 S. Sarkar, T. I. Papon, Z. Zhu, D. Staratzis, and M. Athanassoulis, "Enabling Timely and Persistent Deletion in LSM-Engines", ACM Transactions on Database Systems, 2023.

ICDE 2023 S. Sarkar, N. Dayan, and M. Athanassoulis, "The LSM Design Space and its Read Optimizations", In Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering, 2023.

A. Raman, S. Sarkar, M. Olma, and M. Athanassoulis, "Indexing for Near-Sorted Data", In Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering, 2023.

SIGMOD 2022 S. Sarkar and M. Athanassoulis, "Dissecting, Designing, and Optimizing LSM-based Data Stores", *In Proc. of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data*, 2022.

M. Athanassoulis, S. Sarkar, T. I. Papon, Z. Zhu, and D. Staratzis, "Building Deletion-DEBull 2022 Compliant Data Systems", IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin, vol. 45(1), 2022. S. Sarkar and M. Athanassoulis, "Query Language Support for Timely Data Deletion", In Proc. **EDBT 2022** of the International Conference on Extending Database Technology, 2022. S. Sarkar, D. Staratzis, Z. Zhu, and M. Athanassoulis, "Constructing and Analyzing the LSM **PVLDB 2021** Compaction Design Space", In Proc. of the Very Large Databases Endowment, vol. 14(11), 2021. S. Sarkar, T. I. Papon, D. Staratzis, and M. Athanassoulis, "Lethe: A Tunable Delete-Aware LSM SIGMOD 2020 Engine", In Proc. of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data, 2020. S. Misra, P. K. Bishoyi, and S. Sarkar, "i-MAC: In-Body Sensor MAC in Wireless Body Area SYSTEMS J. 2020 Networks for Healthcare IoT", IEEE Systems Journal, vol. 15(3), 2020. COMM. S. Sarkar, S. Chatterjee, S. Misra, and R. Kudupudi, "Privacy-Aware Blind Cloud Framework **LETTERS 2017** for Advanced Healthcare", IEEE Communications Letters, vol. 21(11), 2017. P. Bhavathankar, S. Sarkar, and S. Misra, "Optimal Decision Rule-Based Ex-ante Frequency COMP. NET. Hopping for Jamming Avoidance in Wireless Sensor Networks", Computer Network, Elsevier, 2017 vol. 128, 2017. S. Sarkar, S. Chatterjee, and S. Misra, "Assessment of the Suitability of Fog Computing in the **TCC 2016** Context of Internet of Things", IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing, vol. 6(1), 2016. S. Sarkar and S. Misra, "From Micro to Nano: The Evolution of Wireless Sensor-Based Health **PULSE 2016** Care", IEEE PULSE, vol. 7(1), 2016. S. Sarkar and S. Misra, "Theoretical Modeling of Fog Computing: A Green Computing **IET NET. 2016** Paradigm to Support IoT Applications", IET Networks, vol. 5(2), 2016. **GLOBECOM** S. Sarkar, S. Misra, and M. S. Obaidat, "Resource Allocation for Wireless Body Area Networks 2016 in Presence of Selfish Agents", In Proc. of the IEEE Global Communications Conference, 2016. S. Sarkar, S. Misra, B. Bandyopadhyay, C. Chakraborty, and M. S. Obaidat, "Performance Anal-TC 2015 ysis of IEEE 802.15.6 MAC Protocol Under Non-ideal Channel Conditions and Saturated Traffic Regime", IEEE Transactions on Computers, vol. 64(10), 2015. S. Misra and S. Sarkar, "Priority-Based Time-Slot Allocation in Wireless Body Area Networks **JBHI 2015** During Medical Emergency Situations: An Evolutionary Game Theoretic Perspective", IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics, vol. 19(2), 2015. CLOUD COMP. S. Sarkar, S. Chatterjee, and S. Misra, "Evacuation and Emergency Management Using a Fed-2014 erated Cloud", IEEE Cloud Computing, vol. 1(4), 2014. S. Sarkar, S. Misra, C. Chakraborty, and M. S. Obaidat, "Analysis of Reliability and Throughput GLOBECOM under Saturation Condition of IEEE 802.15.6 CSMA/CA for Wireless Body Area Networks", 2014 *In Proc. of the IEEE Global Communications Conference*, 2014.

Other Conference and Workshop Papers

	A. Raman, K. Karatsenidis, S. Sarkar, M. Olma, M. Athanassoulis, "BODS: A Benchmark on
TPCTC 2022	Data Sortedness", In Proc. of the TPC Tech. Conf. on Performance Evaluation & Benchmarking, 2022.

iThings 2018 S. Sarkar, J.-P. Banatre, L. Rilling, and C. Morin, "Towards Enforcement of the EU GDPR: Enabling Data Erasure", IEEE International Conference on Internet of Things, 2018.

S. Chatterjee, **S. Sarkar**, and S. Misra, "Quantification of Node Misbehavior in Wireless Sensor Networks: A Social Choice-Based Approach", *IEEE International Conference on Communications Workshops*, 2015.

AIMoC 2015 S. Chatterjee, S. Sarkar, and S. Misra, "Energy-Efficient Data Transmission in Sensor-Cloud", *International Conference on Applications and Innovations in Mobile Computing*, 2015.

Demo Papers

SIGMOD 2023 Z. Zhu, S. Sarkar, and M. Athanassoulis, "Acheron: Persisting Tombstones in LSM Engines", In Proc. of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data, 2023. [Demo website]

S. Sarkar, K. Chen, Z. Zhu, and M. Athanassoulis, "Compactionary: A Dictionary for LSM Compactions", In Proc. of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data, 2022. [Demo website]

Invited Talks and Lectures

Technology Kharagpur, India.

02/2023	"Building Deletion-Compliant Data Systems", University of Massachusetts Boston , USA.
02/2023	"Building Deletion-Compliant Data Systems", Brandeis University , USA.
12/2022	"Constructing and Analyzing the LSM Compaction Design Space", MongoDB, USA.
10/2022	"Toward Building Deletion Compliant Data Systems", HTPS Workshop (<i>Invitation-only</i>), CA, USA.
07/2021	"Enabling Efficient Deletes in Log-Structured KV-Stores", Microsoft Research, Redmond, USA.
02/2021	"Enabling Efficient Deletes in Log-Structured Key-Value Stores", Guest Lecture at Boston University , USA.
07/2020	"Lethe: A Tunable Delete-Aware LSM-Based Storage Engine", Alibaba Cloud, China.
01/2020	"Lethe: A Tunable Delete-Aware LSM-Based Storage Engine", North East DB Day, MIT , USA. [Spotlight talk]
07/2018	"Personal Data Management in Cloud-based IoT", Guest lecture at University of Rennes 1 , France.
03/2018	$\hbox{``Enabling Privacy by Design in the Context of the Internet of Things'', \textbf{University of Rennes 1}, France.$
03/2018	"Enabling Privacy by Design in the Context of the Internet of Things", Université Pierre-et-Marie- Curie , Paris, France.
02/2018	"Enabling Privacy by Design in the Context of the Internet of Things", CentraleSupélec – Rennes Campus , France.
02/2018	"Enabling Privacy by Design in the Context of the Internet of Things", Laboratoire d'InfoRmatique en Image et Systèmes d'information (LIRIS) , Lyon, France.
09/2015	"Fog computing and Internet of Things", Guest Lecture at Indian Institute of Technology Kharag- pur , India.
09/2015	"WBANs: IEEE 802.15.6", Guest Lecture at Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India.

"Importance of WBAN-Based Healthcare in the Context of IoT", Guest Lecture at Indian Institute of

Conference Talks

06/2022	$"Dissecting, Designing, \& Optimizing LSM-based Data Stores", {\bf ACM\ SIGMOD}, Philadelphia, USA.$
06/2022	"Compactionary: A Dictionary for LSM Compactions", ACM SIGMOD, Philadelphia, USA.
04/2022	"Query Language Support for Timely Data Deletion", EDBT, Edinburgh, UK.
08/2021	"Constructing and Analyzing the LSM Compaction Design Space", VLDB, Copenhagen, Denmark.
07/2020	"Lethe: A Tunable Delete-Aware LSM Engine", ACM SIGMOD, Portland, USA.
08/2018	"Towards Enforcement of the EU GDPRR: Enabling Data Erasure", IEEE iThings , Halifax, Canada.
	"Quantification of Node Misbehavior in Wireless Sensor Networks: A Social Choice-Based Approach", IEEE ICC Workshops , London, UK.
06/2015	"Energy-Efficient Data Trransmission in Sensor-Cloud", AIMoC, Kolkata, India.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

<u>Lecturer</u>

Spring, 2023	Course: Data Systems Architectures (CAS CS-561) [Website] Institute: Boston University, MA, USA Student strength: 27 Course evaluation: 5.00/5.00
Spring, 2020	Course: Fundamentals of Computing Systems (CAS CS-350) [Website] Institute: Boston University, MA, USA Student strength: 95 Course evaluation: 4.36/5.00

Teaching assistant

Fall, 2021	Course: Introduction to Database Systems (CAS CS-460) [Website] Institute: Boston University, MA, USA
Fall, 2020	Course: Introduction to Database Systems (CAS CS-460) [Website] Institute: Boston University, MA, USA
Spring, 2019	Course: Data Systems Architectures (CAS CS-591-A1) [Website] Institute: Boston University, MA, USA
Autumn, 2015	Course: Wireless Ad-Hoc and Sensor Networks (IT60119) Institute: Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, India

SUPERVISION AND MENTORSHIP EXPERIENCE

At Boston University

Master students

Shubham Kaushik (Boston University, MA, USA) Yu-Cheng Huang (Boston University, MA, USA)

Jan'23-present Jan'23-present

Dec'13-Jan'14

Kaijie Chen (Boston University, MA, USA) Guanting Chen (Boston University, MA, USA)	Jun'21-Jan'22 Jun'19-Jun'20
Undergraduate students	
Aaron Ang (Boston University, MA, USA)	Nov'22-Present
RISE interns / High school interns	
Venkat Subramanian (Bridgewater-Raritan High School, NJ, USA)	Jul-Aug'22
Grace Sun (Niskayuna High School, NY, USA)	Jul-Aug'22
Naomi Johnson (Amherst Regional High School, MA, USA)	Jul-Aug'19
Kevin Xu (Skyline High School, WA, USA)	Jul-Aug'19
At Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur	
Doctoral candidates	
Pradyumna Bishoi (IIT Kharagpur, India)	Apr-Dec'17
Prasenjit Bhavathankar (IIT Kharagpur, India)	Sep'16-Jan'17
Master students	
Amit Samanta (IIT Kharagpur, India)	May'16-Aug'17
Undergraduate interns	
Rajesh Kudupudi (IIITDM, Kancheepuram, India)	May-Jul'16
Ananya Konar (NIT Durgapur, India)	May-Jul'16
Dipayan Ghatak (IIEST, Shibpur, India)	May-Jul'15
Ezaj Ahmed Ansari (NIT Durgapur, India)	May-Jul'15
Amogh K. Vedamurthy (SBBR Mahajana First Grade College, Mysore, India)	Jan-Mar'15
Khadija Chowdhry (NIT Durgapur, India)	May-Jul'14
Rachit Daga (NIT Durgapur, India)	May-Jul'14
Manmeet Singh Bhogal (NIT Durgapur, India)	May-Jul'14

PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

Organization

Web Chair, ACM SIGMOD, Reproducibility and Availability, 2023, 2022.

Sponsorship Chair, ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC), 2022.

Program committee member

PVLDB, Demonstration, 2023, 2022.

International Conference on Extending Database Technology (EDBT), 2023.

ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC), 2022.

ACM International Conference on Distributed and Event-Based Systems (DEBS), 2022, 2021.

IEEE International Conference on Big Data (BigData), 2022.

Bitan Bandyopadhyay (Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India)

IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE), 2022.

ACM SIGMOD, Demonstration, 2021.

The Web Conference, 2020.

IEEE SmartData, 2019.

ACM SIGMOD, Reproducibility, 2018.

MobiCom workshop on Future Industrial Communication Networks (FICN), 2018.

EuroSys, 2018. (Shadow PC)

International Conference on Advanced Computing, Networking, and Informatics, 2018. International Conference on Advanced Computing and Intelligent Engineering, 2017, 2016.

Reviewer: International journals

International Journal on Very Large Data Bases (VLDBJ), ACM Transactions on Database Systems, Journal of Systems Architecture (Elsevier), IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems, IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing, IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing, IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology, IEEE Transactions on Big Data, IEEE Transactions on Green Communications and Networking, IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics, IEEE Systems Journal, IEEE Communications Letters, IEEE Wireless Communications Letters, IEEE Wireless Communications Magazine, IEEE Communications Magazine, IEEE Vehicular Technology Magazine, International Journal of Communication Systems (Wiley).

Reviewer: Peer-reviewed conferences

CIDR [2023], PVLDB [2022, 2021], IEEE International Conference on Big Data (BigData) [2021, 2017], Euro-Par [2018], International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS) [2017], International Conference on Cloud Computing Technology and Sciences (CloudCom) [2017], IEEE Conference on Network Function Virtualization and Software Defined Networks (NFV-SDN) [2017], IEEE International Conference on Fog and Edge Computing (ICFEC) [2018, 2017], International Conference on Electronics, Communications and Networks (CECNet) [2017], IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC) [2016], International Conference on Software, Telecommunications and Computer Networks (SoftCOM) [2016], IEEE International Conference on Advanced Networks and Telecommunications Systems (ANTS) [2016, 2015], IEEE Students' Technology Symposium (TechSym) [2014].

Last update: 07-Jul-XXIII